<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Comfort to the afflicted. Deliuered in a sermon preached at Pauls-Crosse the xxi. day of May, M. DC. XXVI. Being the last Sunday in Easter terme. By Antony Fawkener, Mast. of Arts, of Iesus Colledge in Oxford</title>
            <author>Fawkner, Antony, b. 1601 or 2.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00581</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10718</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118330</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853537</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853537</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18922</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00581)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18922)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 885:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Comfort to the afflicted. Deliuered in a sermon preached at Pauls-Crosse the xxi. day of May, M. DC. XXVI. Being the last Sunday in Easter terme. By Antony Fawkener, Mast. of Arts, of Iesus Colledge in Oxford</title>
                  <author>Fawkner, Antony, b. 1601 or 2.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by H. Lownes] for Robert Milbourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at Pauls-Crosse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18922:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18922:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>COMFORT TO THE AFFLICTED. DELIVERED IN A SERMON preached at PAVLS-Croſſe the xxi. day of May, M.DC.XXVI. <hi>Being the laſt Sunday in Eaſter Terme.</hi> By ANTONY FAWKENER, Maſt. of Arts, of Ieſus Colledge in OXFORD.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for ROBERT MILBOVRNE. 1626.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Milbourne, framed device of an open book surrounded by beams of light; below the initials of Peter Short, whose device this previously was (McKerrow 278)</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q>ET VSQUE AD NVBES VERITAS TVA</q>
               </head>
               <p>P. S.</p>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18922:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18922:2"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhipfull, Maſter EVERARD FAWKENER, my bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent good Vncle; Grace, mercy and peace in Chriſt IESUS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the providence of Nature, to neceſsitate a retribution of her gifts unto her ſelf. Her matter ſhee lends, neuer fayles her; it may indeed be in ſome ſort corrupted, but no way annihilated. Though man be corrupted, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture looſeth no ſubſtance; but what was lately hers in a humane body, will ſtill be hers though but in duſt and aſhes. If nature can be ſo fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall to ſaue her owne, tis pity that piety ſhould be a looſer. The riuers reſtore unto the Ocean
<pb facs="tcp:18922:3"/>what they have received from her, themſelves: And by an imitating gratitude, wee are bound to devote our ſelves to the ſources of our fortunes. As of the paſſed, you are (next God) the patron of my ſucceeding happineſſe: Wherefore in ſtead of my ſelfe, I am bold to preſent unto you this off-ſpring, and indeed (in reſpect of ſo generall an audience) my firſt borne: which according to the Law, I have already dedicated unto the Lord. A worke of purpoſe proportioned to the hearers benefite, not a Criticks cenſure. So plaine, that the ſimple may underſtand; and yet (I hope) not altogether ſo unpoliſhed, that the friendly and iudiciouſly curious may ſcorne it. Briefly, what I have conſecrated to God, I may boldly preſent to man. Therefore in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of your imitation of him in accepting a good will, I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Nephew, in all Chriſtian dutie to be commanded, ANTONY FAWKENER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18922:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT Pauls-Croſſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOB 19.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Haue pitie vpon me, haue pitie vpon me, (O yee my friends) for the hand of God hath touched mee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the great Vniuerſe, ſo the ſmall World, <hi>Man</hi> is compoſed of, and diuided into two parts; Spirit and Body. The ſoule expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth creatures immateriall; Angells: The body is the character of things mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall and corporall. The world was pure till man fell: the ſinne of the little world curſed the greate one. No ſooner was <hi>Adam</hi> found guilty, but the earth was curſed, and that receiued
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18922:4"/>puniſhment before the delinquent: yet not for its owne, but his ſake. Man ſinned, not the earth; the earth was curſed, not for its owne, but mans puniſhment: The ground muſt be curſed ere man can be puniſhed: the earth muſt be barren, ere <hi>Adam</hi> can ſweat. As of ſinne, ſo is man the chiefe ſubiect of calamitie; each creature elſe for his ſake, he for his owne. Their puniſhment is not theirs, but his; and their vnhappineſſe onely in order to his miſery. The earth indeed was curſt, man more; barrenneſſe ſeiſed on it, death on him.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Rarò antecedentem ſceleſtum</l>
               <l>Deſeruit pede poena claude.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Puniſhment is light-footed, and will as ſoone reuenge God, as man can iniure him. Tranſgreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſometimes puniſhed with the obiect it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. <hi>Adam</hi> indeede by eating the forbidden fruit, knew good and euill; but 'twas a lamentable knowledge. He knew euill, but firſt in himſelfe: the firſt ſcience he had, was of his owne infirmity; for, <hi>He ſaw that he was naked.</hi> Gen. 3.7. Sometimes 'tis puniſh't by the contrary: <hi>Adam</hi> would no ſooner haue beene as God, but he was as man; ambitious to be equall with the Almightie, he became infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to himſelfe. By his owne power he would haue liued for euer, and therefore died preſently; for, <hi>By ſinne death entred into the world.</hi> Loe then! he was no ſooner ſinfull, than miſerable; no ſooner the ſubiect of tranſgreſsion, than of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As then we deriue ſinne from our parents, ſo it's puniſhment, and miſery is as much <hi>ex traduce</hi> as guilt. What man then liues and oft-times ſinnes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18922:4"/>not? what man oft-times ſinnes, and is not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſcourged? As then our affliction may be common, ſo our compunction ſhould be mutuall. Our brother is corrected to day, to morrow may be our courſe: <hi>Iob</hi> was afflicted in this Chapter, he knew his friends might be ere long (as indeed they were in the laſt Chapter, where he was faine to ſacrifice for them:) and therefore exhorts them to beſtow that vpon him in his calamitie, which they would be glad to beg of him in theirs; at leaſt, that weake mercy of commiſeration, and that ſmall ſolace, Pitie.</p>
            <q>Haue pitie vpon me, haue pitie vpon me &amp;c.</q>
            <p>Man and wife are one by a matrimoniall vnion; Body and Soule make one by a naturall conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Each man hath in himſelfe a ſtate Oeconomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call; <hi>Eue</hi> was married to <hi>Adam,</hi> the Body to the Soule. <hi>Adam</hi> then is both <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> Soule and Body. The Serpent firſt beguiled <hi>Eue,</hi> then ſhee <hi>Adam:</hi> Vanity firſt cheats ſenſe, then ſhee deceiues the ſoule. As both haue ſinned, ſo both are puniſhed in the ſame order: Firſt <hi>Eue</hi> was chid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, then <hi>Adam.</hi> Firſt the body is puniſhed in this world, then the ſoule in the life to come. The whole world of man tranſgreſſed in its parts; <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> who were it: and, by a law of pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, each of them is puniſhed in their parts; ſoule and body, which make vp them. The whole man then is afflicted in his parts: looke but vpon this verſe, and behold this afflicted man. My Text is the Embleme of a wretched wight, where by a method Syntheticall, the ſacred limmer proceeds
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18922:5"/>from the parts to the whole. Firſt, there are two petitions correſpondent to two parts: <hi>Haue pitie vpon me:</hi> and againe, <hi>Haue pitie vpon me.</hi> Pitie my body, pitie my ſoule: Both grounded vpon foure implicite reaſons; two taken <hi>à Poſſe;</hi> for you may doe it, becauſe 'tis Eaſie and Lawfull: and two <hi>à Debito;</hi> for you moſt doe it, becauſe 'tis comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Nature and by God. Secondly, the parties petitioned, <hi>O yee my friends.</hi> Thirdly, the reaſons expreſſed on the petitioners part, moouing and perſwading to the grant of his requeſt; which in generall are three: 1. taken from the cauſes of his affliction, which here are two; Inſtrumentall, <hi>ſ. The hand:</hi> prime Efficient, <hi>ſ. Of God.</hi> 2. taken from the action concrete, with its manner, <hi>ſ. Hath touched.</hi> 3. from the patient; the whole man, and but a fraile man, <hi>ſ. Mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then of the double petition: <hi>Haue pitie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, haue pitie vpon me.</hi> Such was the loue of God to vs, that he would not make vs according to any image, but his owne: he would haue had vs no ſooner men than ſonnes; and the Creator vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to be the prototype of his creature. Yet the madneſſe of our ambition fluttered to ſoare aboue the wiſdome of his mercie: <hi>Coelum ipſum petimus ſtultitiâ.</hi> To be duſt and aſhes, was as much as by our owne nature we could be; yet to be but a little inferiour to God, was to be leſſe than wee would be. How faine we would haue beene as God himſelfe! and nothing could ſatisfie the ſtupide pride of our finite nature, ſaue to be abſolutely equall with an inſinite eſſence. So fooliſh was our
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18922:5"/>firſt rebellion, that nothing could be the obiect of its aime, ſaue the vanitie of a contradiction. Thus in defacing his image, we vncreated his worke, and by the defect of a new creation, made our ſelues what he made vs not. Now, if he that is not with him, be againſt him; he that is not like him, is ſo diſlike him, that hee is contrarie. As then we walked ſtubbornely againſt him, ſo hath he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſtubbornely againſt vs, reuenging our diſlike of his likeneſſe, and by his iuſtice puniſhing the contempt of his mercy. So that now our miſerie is ſquared to our happineſſe, and our ſenſe as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally admits the obiect that it hates, as that it likes. The eye can as eaſily ſee a ghaſtly pale, as a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing white; our fleſh may be as ſoone ſcorched with heate, as recreated by a refreſhing luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmth. The eare can as properly heare the Toade as the Nighingale, and all our ſenſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue as naturally their puniſhments as their bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings. Nor is the ſoule exempted from this afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but muſt haue as great a ſhare with the body in miſerie as it had in ſinne; which though it haue not ſenſe, it may haue a compaſſion and a fellow-feeling by the vertue of its vnion. It willes the wel-fare of its neareſt neighbour, the body; which being tortur'd its deſire is croſſed, and the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the will is the tarteſt puniſhment of the ſoule.<note place="margin">Aquin. de ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. q. vlt.</note> My Text is compaſſed with the complaint of this double affliction, as the man of the Text <hi>(Iob)</hi> is with the miſerie it ſelfe; He cries out in the 20. verſe, <hi>My bone cleaueth to my skin, and I haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped with the skin of my teeth.</hi> Loe the diſtreſſe of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18922:6"/>his bodie. Againe he expoſtulates in the 22. verſe, <hi>Why doe you perſecute me as God, and are not ſatisfied with my fleſh?</hi> Loe here the anguiſh of his ſoule. This double affliction then may well require a two-fold petition for a two-fold commiſerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Haue pitie vpon me, haue &amp;c.</hi> Thus farre the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition hath reſpected the two-fold ſubiect of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie. Now, becauſe that requeſt is neuer perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorie, which intercedes by the mediation of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, 'tis beſt we ſhould a-while haue reſpect vnto the foure implicite reaſons; two taken <hi>à Poſſe,</hi> for 'tis eaſie and lawfull; and two <hi>á Debito,</hi> for 'tis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Nature and God. And firſt of the firſt,<note place="margin">Eaſie.</note> Tis eaſie. To be bad when there is a poſſibility for vs to be good, argues a neglect; to be bad when it is eaſie to be good, inferres a voluntarie rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It would be an unnaturall contumacie to ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle againſt an offred vertue, and a ſtuddied ſinne to be vicious with difficulty. Teares are as eaſie as affection, and compaſſion as common as loue. If our friend be well, we muſt needes ioy, and if he be ill, by the ſame neceſſitie we muſt weepe: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Xenoph: hiſt. graec. lib. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> If we can ioy, we can grieue; teares are common to both, and each of them equally challenge a compaſſion. As eaſily as we can embrace, we can pitie; and be with as little difficultie compaſſionate, as paſſionate. It is a trouble to be hard hearted, and it was more paine for <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to refraine himſelfe than to weepe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.1. 'Tis no labour to be pitifull; for they that are weakeſt, are moſtinclined to it; Women. <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that could ride in a Chariot, was hard hearted; but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18922:6"/>his daughter, a Virgin, not capable of labour, had compaſſion vpon <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod: 2.6.</note> The men were dogged that could ſtriue againſt commiſeration, and thoſe children of Iſrael which wept at Chriſts death,<note place="margin">S. Luk. 23.28.</note> were the Daughters of Ieruſalem. So eaſie it is for that ſex to pitie,<note place="margin">Athanaſ. q. act Antioch. <hi>88.</hi>
               </note> which by its nature is not of force to rebell againſt its nature. Pitie then is our owne, for it is ingraffed; tis harder to be ſtonie than re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting, and a prodigie to be cruel, none to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> tells vs that ſignes and miracles are the onely effects of Gods power, but loue and compaſſion are the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall fruits of mans will. So that we need not take paines to entertaine lenitie, ſith 'tis in our owne power to be mercifull. Thus condolencie is ſo properly, ſo genuinely ours, that we can hardly be vnmercifull; and therefore in the fable of <hi>Lycaon,</hi> the Poet iudiciouſly makes it the miraculous worke of a ſtrange metamorphoſis, for a man to become a Wolfe. We are ſo our ſelues when we are compaſſionate, that when we are vnmercifull we are not our ſelues.<note place="margin">Athanaſ. ad Antioe. q. <hi>118.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Hardneſſe of heart is not the worke of the creation, but of the Deuill; and crueltie alwaies followes either a baſe or a domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering diſtemperature.<note place="margin">Aqui. <hi>22</hi> ae. q. <hi>30.</hi> Art. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> The proud cannot brooke pitie, ſuppoſing all, ſaue themſelues (who are worſt) worthy of puniſhment. He that is iniured is an enemie to it, for he imagines reuenge; and he that is iniurious, for he is only intent on malice.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18922:7"/>Briefly, it is a ſtranger to the fearleſſe, deſperate and the cowardly fearefull: the one is ſo careleſſe of himſelfe, that he forgets to pitie another; the other is ſo carefull of himſelfe, that he hath no leiſure to pitie another. Loe here the quintaine, the troupe of the Deuill; Pride, Reuenge, Malice, Deſpaire, and Feare; the lame and crooked nurſes of vnmercifulneſſe. The defects of nature are the ſources of crueltie, and the diſtemperatures of the ſoule, the ſole enemies of compaſſion. Yet (good God) how well we could be ought but what we are! we could performe any thing ſaue our taske, and be eaſily compaſſionate if it were not eaſie. Thus doe we warre againſt pietie; chuſing rather to be vicious with difficultie, than vertuous with eaſe. Rather than we will be good, we will ſweate to be bad; and by a miſ-guided election, rather ſeeke a Viper which we know will ſting vs, than receiue any refection which we know will nouriſh vs. Thus when God offers vs bread, we chooſe a ſtone; he giues vs a fiſh, and we aske a ſerpent. But ſtay: our nature is ſo bad, that it will be good, though but by its owne iuſtification. Rather than our iudgements ſhall faile, our inuentions ſhall preuadicate. Malignant mindes muſt be conſtant, though againſt reaſon; and will ſtriue to prooue that bad, which they cannot indure ſhould be ſtiled good. Tis no argument (they'l ſay) to prooue compaſſion good, becauſe tis eaſie; for ſo moſt ſins ſhould be iuſtified. The anſwer to which, drawes vs to the conſideration of the ſecond rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for tis not barely eaſie, but withall iuſtifiable: 'tis Lawfull.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:18922:7"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Lawfull. Zenoph. memor. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Tis <hi>Xenophons</hi> iudgement: what is iuſt, is lawfull; and what is reaſonable, is iuſt. Vertue is meaſured by reaſon, and hath principally its nature from election. Reaſon is a diuine gift, though it be naturall, and can aſwell make a vertue, as ſenſe a vice. The fleſh is weake; I but the ſpirit is willing: an intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate body may deſire badly: but a well guided ſoule makes the action vertuous. Mercie,<note place="margin">Aqui. <hi>22</hi> ae. q. <hi>30.</hi> Art <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> as a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue paſſion, may be meere triuiall and idle: Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as a motion of the minde, guided by reaſon, is a beautifull vertue. Now becauſe vertue hath its extreames, and the Deuill can turne himſelfe from blacke to white; from the extreame to appeare the meane; from the Prince of darkneſſe to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me an Angell of light: we muſt ſeeke how to finde the meane, and refuſe the extreames; to entertaine the Angell, and caſt out the Deuill. To the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of which, we muſt firſt define Pitie, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what it is; then, manifeſt the perſons whom it reſpects. But before we proceede to define, let Logicke moderate vs; for becauſe of the ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous terme <hi>Miſericordia,</hi> Mercie, tis beſt to diuide. Tis taken then two waies, as only intimating com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration, or withall implying ſuccour.<note place="margin">In <hi>4.</hi> Pſalm. poenitent.</note> S. <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> makes the diuiſion, and proportions fit termes to the diuiding members. <hi>Per miſericordiam mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerentis affectum intelligimus, per miſerationem verò miſericordiae exhibitionem ſignamus.</hi> The word is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taken for a naked pitie, onely commiſerating misfortunes, without giuing reliefe: or for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion attended with a beneficence, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18922:8"/>an actuall exhibition of ſuccour. The firſt is moſt properly meant in my Text, the ſecond is a naturall conſequent: both may be handled; but to auoyde confuſion and tediouſneſſe, the firſt onely in the doctrine.</p>
            <p>Pitie then is defined to be <hi>Alienae miſeriae in corde noſtro compaſsio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Aug. de ciu. dei, lib. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> a deepe and hearty fellow-feeling of anothers miſerie. From which obſerue theſe foure Canons. Firſt, there muſt be a feeling or ſorrow. Thus in the extremity of commiſeration the Prophet cryeth, <hi>My bowells ſhall ſound like an Harpe for Moab, &amp; mine inward parts for Kirhareſh; Iſay.</hi> 16.11. Secondly, there muſt be a fellow-fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; compaſſion as well as paſſion: for we muſt <hi>ſlere cum flentibus;</hi> weepe with thoſe that weepe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.15. Thirdly, we muſt haue a reſpect to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie; <hi>Miſericordiae propriaſedes miſeria eſt,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard:</hi>
               <note place="margin">De conuerſ. ad Cler. ſer. cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> Felicitie requires no pitie, but miſerie is the only ſeate of mercy. Laſtly, it muſt be <hi>Alienae miſcria,</hi> of anothers vnhappines. Our pitie hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to others, not our ſelues; and if we are ſad for our own miſerie, 'tis <hi>Dolor,</hi> not <hi>Compaſsio;</hi> Anguiſh, not Pitie. Sothen, if we haue not feeling, we are not paſſionate; if we haue not fellow-feeling, we are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſionate. The definition then includes a re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on, &amp; that reſpect brings vs to the perſons. The conſideration of whom ſwayes the ballance, and makes our pitie either friuolous or diſcreet. Now the perſons to be itied, are to be conſidered in reſpect of their coniunction to the parties pity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: The coniunction may be three-fold, 1. Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, as of a Kinſman to a Kinſman;<note place="margin">Aqui. <hi>22.</hi> ae. q. <hi>31.</hi> Art. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Ciuill, as of a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18922:8"/>Countriman to a Countriman; 3. Spirituall, as of a Chriſtian to a Chriſtian. We ought indeede to pitie all, but theſe <hi>per prius.</hi> Charitie begins at home: we owe it to each man, but firſt to the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. Vertue and Grace ('tis <hi>Aquin as</hi> his ſimile) imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Nature; the fire firſt warmes what is like it, and next it. The ayre can ſooner participate of the fires heate, than the water; and the flame ſooneſt heats that which naturally is moſt propenſe and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to warmth. So though our Compaſsion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to all, it firſt reſpects the neareſt. Religion and policie preſcribe an order to our loue, and naturally our affection is as neere as nature.<note place="margin">In Cant. Tom. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Puto quidem eſſe vim charitatis vnam, multas tamen ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere cauſas &amp; multos ordines diligendi,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Origen.</hi> We may loue, and conſequently pitie, all; yet ſome firſt and moſt, and one commiſeration may haue diuers degrees. The beautifull and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed may be both beloued, yet the faireſt beſt: I may commiſerate a friends caſe, yea and an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies too, yet my friends firſt. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> fed all Egypt, but he placed his father and his brethren in the beſt of the land, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.11. He ſold foode to the Egyptians, <hi>verſe</hi> 14. but hee nouriſhed them; verſ. 12. S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſuffered perſecution for the Gentiles, but he could wiſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſeparated from Chriſt for his bretheren his kinſmen according to the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.3. <hi>Iſrael</hi> was commanded to entertaine ſtrangers gently, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19.33. but they wept bittery for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of their countrimen the Beniamites;<note place="margin">2. Sam. 21.3.</note> 
               <hi>Iudg.</hi> 21.2. <hi>Dauid</hi> indeed pitied and reuenged the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18922:9"/>ſoiourning Iebuſites: But <hi>Ieremy</hi> compiled a whole booke of <hi>Lamentations</hi> for his natiue City Ieruſalem.<note place="margin">Gen. 19.4.6.</note> Briefly, <hi>Abraham</hi> may be kinde to <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar,</hi> but he muſt loue <hi>Sarah.</hi> It was grieuous in his ſight to part with <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> yet he muſt not be heire with his ſonne <hi>Iſaack:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 21.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>For we muſt doe good to all men, but ſpecially to thoſe that are of the houſhould of faith, Gal.</hi> 6.10. Theſe three things then, Religion, Kindred, and Country, claime the firſt title in our affection, and conſequently in our compaſſion; and that commiſeration which orderly reſpects them, is naturall, lawfull, and ſanctified. Theſe indeed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre a priority in mercy, but inſinuate not ſo clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the legitimacy of Pitie it ſelfe. Now this law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe we may collect from the motiues to commiſeration, and the cauſes of affliction. The motiues are of two ſorts, 1. <hi>A parte miſerentis,</hi> 2. <hi>à parte eius cuius miſeremur:</hi> the one is grounded in the party pitying, the other proceeds from the perſon pitied. The cauſes of compaſſion, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the perſon pitying, are three: 1. <hi>Dilectio.</hi> 2. <hi>Coniunctio.</hi> 3. <hi>Aſsimilatio:</hi> Loue, Kindred and equalitie, or likeneſſe. The firſt is Loue: There is a body as well by loue as by nature; the difference is, that two naturall bodies make but one by friendſhip. As one naturall body hath onely its owne ſenſe, ſo two bodies, made one by friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, hath but one feeling. So that pitie is as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall as ſenſe, and compaſſion as proper to friends as paſſion to men. All things are common amongſt friends; then ſo is miſerie: for affliction is as ſelfe-communicatiue as happineſſe. <hi>My friend is as mine
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18922:9"/>owne ſoule, Deut.</hi> 13.6. Thus if I loue my friend, I am but <hi>penè alter,</hi> ſcarce another; ſo that I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count his paine my griefe, and what he vndergoes properly, I muſt ſuffer, at leaſt by reputation. The ſecond motiue is Coniunction and neareneſſe; which we haue before touched. The third is Aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milation or likeneſſe. If the winde can ſcatter duſt, then <hi>à ſimili,</hi> why cannot the breath of Gods no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrills ſcatter vs which are but duſt? If one man be in miſerie, we are men too, &amp; but men, and may be iuſt ſo afflicted. <hi>Aetas parentum peior auis</hi>— we are all no better than our brethren; not ſo good as our fathers. If they be puniſhed, ſo may we; if bad be ſcourged, why ſhould worſe looke for happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? If <hi>Iob</hi> be puniſhed, why may not his friends be tormented? <hi>Saul</hi> perſecutes <hi>Dauid;</hi> and what <hi>Superſedeas</hi> hath hee, but that for all that the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims may ſcorne him? <hi>Iacob</hi> was as wiſe, as aged, and pitied the Shechemites his neighbours, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the reſt of his neighbours might ere long haue had cauſe to pitie him: If the inhabitants of the land ſhould haue gathered themſelues toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt him being few in number, and ſo he and his houſe ſhould haue beene deſtroyed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.30. If then we pitie others, we put our compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to vſe; we lend our mercie to our owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and onely ſtore it to receiue it at neede. Thus our mercie reflects vpon vs, and our compaſſion to others includes as much reſpect to our ſelues as them. Now if we ſhould onely pitie them for our owne ſakes, it would be <hi>Philautie,</hi> not Charitie; a ſelfe-affection, not a brotherly compaſſion. There
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18922:10"/>muſt be then <hi>cauſa</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as well as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; The obiect muſt impell to, as much as we in our ſelues can be mooued to grant. So that we muſt weigh the motiues, aſwell in reſpect of the partie pitied, as the partie pitying. Now that motiue is onely one, Miſerie; which in reſpect of the perſon, its ſubiect, is two-fold. Involuntary; which befalls vs againſt our will: and voluntarie, which in ſome manner takes ground from our owne conſent. Involuntarie vnhappineſſe is of two ſorts; Either Naturall, when any defect is in and by Nature: as blindneſſe, lameneſſe, and ſuch like imperfections vnauoidable: Or caſuall, as when from any thing we expect good,<note place="margin">Iob 1. 2. Sam. 4.4.</note> and it happens euill. So <hi>Iobs</hi> children met to be familiar and merry together, and the houſe fell vpon them. So <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> in haſt to be ſaued, was lamed. Theſe two ſorts of vnhappineſſe, may iuſtly cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge pitie. Wherfore Chriſt had compaſſion vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the blinde man, <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.6. and <hi>Dauid</hi> vpon lame <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.10. Now our calamitie may be termed voluntary two wayes; <hi>Ratione non euitationis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aqui. 22ae. q. <hi>30.</hi> Art. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; ratione electionis in cauſâ.</hi> Eyther in not auoyding it when we may; as when either by contempt or neglect we runne head-long into any imminent danger: Or in willing vnhappineſſe in its cauſe; which is, when we will the cauſe of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie; for ſo conſequently we will miſerie it ſelfe. He that eates knowne poyſon, doth in ſome man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner deſire ſickneſſe. He that wills the tranſgreſſion of the law, willes conſequently the puniſhment. He that muſt needs ſin, muſt needs die; and he that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18922:10"/>willes the one, deſires the other. Iſrael will die if they will ſin: wherfore God (as it were wondring at their vnnaturall deſire) askes them not why they will ſinne, but why they will die, <hi>Ezskiel</hi> 33.11. So theſe two ſorts are ſo farre from moouing to pitie, that they excite to puniſhment. So then, all poore are not alike to be pitied. <hi>Cain</hi> was a wanderer, ſo was <hi>Iacob:</hi> but <hi>Cain</hi> a Vagabond, <hi>Iacob</hi> a Pilgrim; the one to be puniſhed, the other to be relieued. He that will not auoide an apparent affliction, is worthy to receiue it.<note place="margin">1. King. 2.37.46.</note> And if <hi>Shimei</hi> wil not keepe his bounds, but raſhly goe ouer the riuer Kidron, good reaſon hee ſhould be ſmitten that he die. <hi>Bona eſt miſericordia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Aug. ſup-Exod. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſed non debet eſſe contra iudicium,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> Mercy is good, but then inordinate, when againſt iuſtice. We know by the immutable decree of God, that bloud is to be ſhed for bloud: If then the murtherer will needs be glutted with bloud, let him buy it with the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his owne; and receiue what conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he wills, the puniſhment.<note place="margin">Deut. 19.21.</note> His bloud ſhall be vpon him, and our eie muſt not pitie him. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, voluntarie affliction doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes exclude commiſeration, but only, or at leaſt chiefly when it is offenſiue to Iuſtice. <hi>Miſereremei, non quia dignus, ſed quia inops &amp; pauper ſum ego. Iuſtitia meritum quaerit, miſericordia miſeriam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuetur. Ver a miſericordia non iudicat, ſed afficit.</hi> Thus S. <hi>Bernard</hi> teacheth how to aske mercy by his owne petition. Haue compaſſion (ſaith he) vpon me, not becauſe I deſerue it, but becauſe I want it.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18922:11"/>Iuſtice lookes for merit; Mercie takes notice of miſerie; and true commiſeration argues not by reaſon, but affects with paſsion. <hi>Samuel</hi> mourned for diſobedient <hi>Saul,</hi> reſpecting his diſtreſſe not his ſinne. And <hi>Dauid</hi> ſorrowed for that trayterous parricide, <hi>Abſalom:</hi> his teares indeed were in vaine, yet they were pious becauſe pitifull. We may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow pitie vpon an offendour that is dying; not to ſaue him, but to comfort him: we may pitie an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendour that is liuing,<note place="margin">Aqui <hi>22.</hi> ae q. <hi>31.</hi> Art. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ad ſuſtentationem naturae, non ad fomentum culpae.</hi> We may haue compaſsion vpon his nature in which he is like vs, and not cheriſh his vice, in which we ſhould be diſlike him. From theſe it is euident, how far compaſsion is lawfull, and how inordinate. But becauſe the word Lawfull may only inſinuate a tolerancie (for things indifferent, and not in themſelues abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good, may be permitted, and according to that acceptation lawfull) the next reaſon challenges place; which is grounded vpon command: and firſt of Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Nature. Arban. q. <hi>118.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> God hath ſo guided Nature, that ſhee makes her beſt workes, as like as ſhee can to God. Man was created according to his owne image, and is naturally in nothing more like him than in mercy. In each creature there is <hi>veſtigium creatoris,</hi> the foot-ſteppe of the creator; in man his image. The moſt ſauage cruelty hath its li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits: Beares agree amongſt themſelues; and the <hi>Canibals</hi> that deuoure their enemies, nouriſh their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18922:11"/>neighbours. As bodies are naturally contiguous, ſo are our affections: Wee are as neere by loue as they by touch. A man had as good be a ſtocke, as a man without a neighbour. Wee are better than beaſts only in diſcourſe; ſo that our perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on depends vpon a fellow. The cauſe why this fellowſhip is ſo neceſſarie, is the neceſsity of a mutuall reliefe; which is as well afforded by compaſſion, as in a gift. My minde may be as liberall as my hand; and if pouertie curbe my bounty, yet maugre misfortune I can beſtow the naturall beneuolence of pitty: Which is to be accepted, ſith it was the commendations of <hi>Ageſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Xenoph orat. de Ageſilao.</note> Hee reſpected thoſe friends that would doe him a curteſie, more than thoſe that could doe it; preferring the beneuolence of minde, to the poſſible beneficence of fortune. If I cannot grieue, yet I can loue; if by misfortune I cannot ſuccour, yet by nature I can pity. By commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration though I cannot free my friend, yet I can eaſe him, Nor is it my ſorrow that ſo helpes him,<note place="margin">Aqui. 12ae. q. <hi>8.</hi> Art. <hi>2.3.</hi>
               </note> but its cauſe, Affection: for it addes ioy to the afflicted, that hee is beloued euen to compaſſion. As wee are men, wee muſt be ſociable; if wee bee ſociable, when occaſion ſerues wee muſt pitty. That loue is counterfeit which cannot grieue, &amp; ſocietie is nothing worth without ſymphathie. So rarely inbred is this paſsion, that there is ſcarce any thing attained ſo eaſily,<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> and good ſo natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Miſericordia pias mentes ad compaſsionem dolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18922:12"/>neceſſario cogit affectu,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard.</hi> Mercie is ſo naturall to good mindes, that it doth not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade to compaſſion, but compell. So that though they would not pitie, yet they muſt; it being to them ſo naturall that it is vnauoidable. Now as nature rules the creatures, ſo the Creator rules na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; ſo that her preſcript is but ſubordinate to his law, and ſhee onely proclaimes what God firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees. Thus we may inferre that it is Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, becauſe hers; but by reaſon that we may ſee the Almighties will in the bright mirrour the Scripture clearer than in that dimme one of Nature, 'tis ſafeſt to haue recourſe to it, where we ſhall finde that alſo: It is commanded by God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſtote miſericordes, ſicut &amp; pater veſter eſt miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, S. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.36. <hi>Be yee mercifull as your Father is mercifull. Actum eſt.</hi> A further proofe might ſauour of incredulitie. Loe here the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand both of God and Nature; 'tis the Decree of Ieſus Chriſt, God and Man. In which is a precept and an exhortation. He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands by his power, <hi>Be yee mercifull;</hi> and perſwades by an example; <hi>Sicut pater &amp;c. As your Father is mercifull.</hi> That ſtatute muſt needs be good, which God enacts, and that action muſt needs therefore be iuſt, of which he is the example. Our firſt parents deſired to be as God, and their ambition was rebellion. Yet loe we muſt labour to be as God, and our deſire ſhall be religion. To aſpire to be equall with God, is trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt his Maieſtie: to indeauour to be like him, is obedience to his precept. The pride of their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18922:12"/>ambition attempted an equalitie; but the loue of our obedience aimes at a likeneſſe. His mercie is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all his workes, wherefore if you will be moſt like him, <hi>Eſtote miſericordes; Be you mercifull;</hi> ſo you ſhall be as neere him by aſſimilation, as your firſt parents were diſtant by their ambition. Their vainly intended equalitie was puniſhed with iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and your likeneſſe in mercy ſhall be rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with mercy.<note place="margin">Aqui. 22ae. q. <hi>30.</hi> Art. <hi>2.</hi> ad <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Deus non miſeretur niſi propter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morem in quantum nos amat vt aliquid ſui,</hi> ſaith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas.</hi> God therefore pities vs, becauſe he loues vs, and onely loues vs becauſe we are like him. He will pitie the mercifull, becauſe he loues them, and he will loue them becauſe they are ſo like him. Wherfore he will be mercifull vnto the mercifull; and therefore <hi>Bleſſed are the mercifull, for they ſhall obtaine mercie,</hi> S. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.7. Heark beloued; <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the mercifull,</hi> not barely happie; honoured with riches of god, not with the ſlender opulency of fortune. Are there any then amongſt you (my brethren) which haue cloathed Chriſt when he was naked, fed him when hee was hungrie, and giuen him drinke when he was thirſtie? if there be any, <hi>Come yee bleſſed of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Math. 25.24.25.26.</note> 
               <hi>and inherit the kingdome, prepared for you from the foundations of the world.</hi> Inherit that in this world by the ſtable poſſeſsion of a certaine hope, which you ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit in the life to come, in the fulneſſe of ioy for euermore. Be not ſlow to pitie, for it is eaſie; bee not doubtfully curious to receiue it, for it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: Refuſe it not ſtubbornly, ſith 'tis naturall; at
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18922:13"/>leaſt condemne it not rebelliouſly: for 'tis the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God. Pitie thy kinſmen with <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> for they are thy fleſh. Haue compaſsion vpon thy countrimen with <hi>Ieremy,</hi> for they are thy brethren: Be mercifull to thoſe of thy religion, for yee are one in Chriſt Ieſus; yee are of one houſhold of faith. Pitie thy brother for his owne ſake; for ſo thou maieſt comfort him: haue compaſsion vpon him for thine own ſake; for ſo thou maieſt expect a retributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thy miſery. Giue vnto the poore, &amp; ſo lend vnto the Lord, and he wil pay thee: or giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poore, &amp; ſo pay vnto the Lord what he hath lent thee. <hi>Quid habes quod non accepiſti?</hi> What haſt thou, which thou haſt not receiued? &amp; what canſt thou beſtow, but what thou haſt borrowed? If thou giueſt to the poore, thou giueſt to Chriſt; if thou giueſt to Chriſt, thou giueſt to God: Nor is it ſo much a gift as a debt;<note place="margin">S. Aug: in. Pſal. <hi>147.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Deillius das qui iubet vt des.</hi> May not God do what he wil with his own? If his eye be good, let not yours be therefore euill. For what you beſtow is none of yours, but his only that commands you to giue it. If then God forgiue thee thy debt, take not thy brother by the throat for his. Doth the poore owe thee any thing? re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it: for in hauing more than is neceſſary for thee, thou oweſt as much to him. If thou haſt more than thou needeſt, thou haſt more than thine own. <hi>Superflua diuitum neceſſaria ſunt pauperum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem. ibid.</note> The ouerplus of the rich are the neceſſaries of the poore. A niggardly hand may oppreſſe as much as a violent.<note place="margin">Idem. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Res alienae poſsidentur, cum ſuperflua poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur.</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18922:13"/>When you whoord vp that which you do not want, you ſpoyle the poore of that which they want. <hi>Anobis extrahitur crudeliter quod conſumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur inaniter.</hi> That is cruelly extorted from the needy, which is lauiſhly ſpent vpon thy luſt. Sith then God hath giuen to thee, imitate him in being bountifull to thy brother. Let Gods almes be thy almes, and what his mercie hath beſtowed vpon thee, let thy pitie diuide vnto thy neighbour. Briefly, though the Shabeans robbe <hi>Iob,</hi> yet let <hi>Eliphaz</hi> pity him: though the Lord by affliction trye him yet let <hi>Bildad</hi> and <hi>Zophar</hi> haue compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vpon him; and though he be perſecuted by Satan his enemie, yet at leaſt, Haue pitie vpon him (O yee his friends). <hi>Friends!</hi> yea, but very ſmall ones; In my Text they are put in a parentheſis, and are no neerer than almoſt quite out. Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie may haue choiſe of acquaintance; but onely miſerie is the touch-ſtone of a friend. 'Tis true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the Man of the Eaſt had diuers friends, but now they abhorre, and are turned againſt the poore man, <hi>Iob, Iob.</hi> 19.19. So fickle is the amity of paraſiticall friends, that the inconſtancy of time and fortune can ſterne its Nature. Now if we will loue conſtantly, we muſt loue well; and if we will loue well, we muſt loue vertuouſly. So that our friendſhip muſt principally reſpect goodneſſe, both in our ſelues and friends. He that cannot af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect himſelfe, cannot affect another; and he that loues iniquitie, cannot loue himſelfe: For he hates his owne ſoule, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 11.15. <hi>Cum ergo ediſſem
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18922:14"/>animam meam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Aug. ad Mart epiſt. <hi>155.</hi> de verâ amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ.</note> 
               <hi>verum amicum quomodò habere pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, ea mihi optantem in quibus ipſe meipſum patie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar inimicum?</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtin.</hi> If in louing ſinne I hate my ſoule, how can my vicious friend be my true friend, which onely can wiſh that content vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, the deſire of which makes me an enemy to my ſelfe? If then our ſelues be bad, we cannot loue our friends wel: &amp; again, if our friends be bad they cannot loue vs well. The wicked is alwayes conſcious of his owne vnfaithfulneſſe, and iealous of his fellowes conſtancy by his guiltineſſe of his owne inconſtancy; he loues without truſt, as if he would one day hate, and his friendſhip is alwaies ſtartled with ſuſpition. The vicious then cannot loue, for they dare not truſt; though they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate and ioyned by company, they are diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in heart: ſo that religion onely and goodneſſe can vnite the ſoules. A vertuous friend-ſhip cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects Nature, and what ſhee hath diuided in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, it makes one in affection. Wherefore the Poet liuely inſinuates the neareneſſe of friends by diuiding their ſoule: as though there were not two ſoules,<note place="margin">Hor. Od. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Od. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> but one parted; ſo that himſelfe had but <hi>—Animae dimidium—</hi> halfe a ſoule; his friend had the other part,<note place="margin">Confeſ. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> and they two had but one life. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> commends this moſt ſignificant and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſiue deſcription of true friendſhip by ſharing of ſpirits, and the Scripture properly exemplifies in two religious friends; for the ſoule of <hi>Ionathan</hi> was knit with the ſoule of <hi>Dauid,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.1. So almoſt were they one, that they could not be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18922:14"/>two; and the only difference between them was, that each might be but halfe the other. This amitie is as conſtant as neare, and cannot be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, vnleſſe the friend ſhould be vnioynted from himſelfe. If <hi>Iobs</hi> friends had beene ſuch, his petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would haue beene granted before framed; and as ſoone as he had felt affliction, he might haue demanded pitie by the title of a Symphathie. But they are not ſo affectionate as to condole, nor ſo neare as to haue a fellow-feeling. Wherefore if he will require compaſſion, he muſt pleade for it; which he doth in the next place, by ſhewing the cauſes of his affliction. and firſt the inſtrumentall: <hi>For the hand of God hath touched me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The hand. De ſerm. Dom. in mont. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quemadmodum in oculo contemplatio, ſic in manu actio intelligitur,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> The eye and the hand are the principall inſtruments of ſenſe. The one of ſeeing, the nobler ſenſe of diſcipline: The other of feeling, the moſt neceſſarie to the ſimple being. So that as we vnderſtand contemplation by the Eye,<note place="margin">In lib. Reg. cap. <hi>1.</hi> Hom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> ſo we intimate power and action by the hand. <hi>Per manus intelliguntur opera,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Origen.</hi> The hand is the moſt operatiue inſtrument of the will; and what we doe by it commonly, we expreſſe by it. So that nature hath eſtabliſhed it a cuſtome: and in moſt common-wealths at any publicke election,<note place="margin">Hiſt. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> the motion of the hand declares the aſſent of the will. <hi>Vultu manu<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aſſentiebantur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tacitus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſidorus lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> In the Romane Senat they mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted feſted their conſent by holding vp their hands; and in their Armies too, to auoide the confuſion
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18922:15"/>of vocal ſuffrages, it was a militarie cuſtome to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie their mindes by their hands: withall intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by that inſtrument of vigour and force, not onely their approbation, but alſo their conſtancie and readineſſe to the maintaining their reſolution ſo expreſſed. The Scriptures are as copious of te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, as their authors of cuſtomes. We will vrge a few. Firſt, God himſelfe in a ſolemne Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation is ſaid to lift vp his Hand, <hi>Num.</hi> 14.30. inſinuating the maintenance of his decree by his power. The light of his countenance can bleſſe his people; but when he miraculouſly deliuers them and plagues his enemies, 'tis with a mightie Hand. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.12. The ſigne of ſtrength is in a ſtretched out arme; and if Iſrael will conquer <hi>Amaleck, Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> muſt ſtay vp <hi>Moſes</hi> Hands, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17 12. Alas weake <hi>Iob!</hi> If the Hand of God be his power, and that wholly vpon thee, thy friends had neede pitie thee. The hand that can ſpan the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, muſt needes ſquieze a worme. The Finger of God was enough to plague a whole great na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Aegypt, <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.19. Was it then poſſible that one miſerable man ſhould ſuſtaine the weight of his whole hand? <hi>Qui dat pati dat poſſe pati.</hi> He that ſends affliction will ſend patience. God is merciful as well as iuſt, and it was the <hi>Hand of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet that might be a queſtion,<note place="margin">God.</note> if it were not an axiome, and be diſputed as but probable, if the Holy Ghoſt did not warrant the neceſſitie: God approued of <hi>Iob,</hi> whom the Deuill ſlandered: Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan ſmote him with boiles, <hi>Iob.</hi> 2.7. Then, was that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18922:15"/>the Hand of God? <hi>Malignus ſpiritus malâ volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate nocere appetit; tamen nocendi poteſtatem non ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad Simpl. l. <hi>2.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>niſi ab illo ſub quo ſunt omnia certis &amp; iuſtis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorum gradibus ordinata.</hi> Thus S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> anſweres; The Deuill would hurt, but he wants the power: God muſt giue him leaue, elſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not execute his will. Satan hath the will in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but he cannot performe it, vnleſſe God lend him power. The cauſe is Gods, and Satan cannot perſecute till he will proſecute. God of himſelfe is iuſt, and Satan malitious; &amp; vnleſſe God wil exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his iuſtice, Satan cannot actuate his malice. So that Gods permiſſion is his action and the power that he lends, is ſtiled his <hi>Hand.</hi> God is Iudge, Satan the executioner; 'tis the Deuills will, but Gods power. Now the Lambe is mercifull, but the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon is cruell; and though Satans malice would cruſh vs, yet the hand of God will but Touch vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hath touched.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Touched.</note> And 'tis enough; for at the touch of the Lord, the mountaines ſmoake: and are the wicked any thing ſaue an heape of tranſgreſſion? is the world of man ought elſe ſaue a mountaine of ſinne? We are nothing ſaue a lumpe of diſorder, a Babel of contumacie, built ſo high that our rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion may reach to Gods cares, and need not with the bloud of <hi>Abel,</hi> crie, but whiſper for a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance: a fraile maſſe of confuſion, on which if he doth but blow, he puffes vs into a nothing; and if he wil but touch this Babylon, our ſmoake muſt aſcend for euermore. Yet is he not more iuſtice than mercie, &amp; can expreſſe himſelfe to be both at
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18922:16"/>once. So that the Scripture attributes to him a three-fold touch, <hi>ſ. Tactum iuſticiae, tactum miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiae, &amp; tactum medium,</hi> or <hi>tentationis.</hi> He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds by the touch of iuſtice, when hee will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge; So the Lord of hoſts ſhall touch the land, and it ſhall melt away, <hi>Amos.</hi> 9.5. He comforteth by the touch of his mercie, when he will forgiue; for ſo Ieſus touched the Leper, and he was healed, S. <hi>Math.</hi> 8.3. He toucheth by the touch of his mercie and iuſtice together, when he will trie; and ſo the hand of God hath touched <hi>Iob.</hi> In whoſe tryall, reſpect the affliction, and view Gods Iuſtice; looke vpon the end, and behold his mercie. He was ſinfull, therefore might lawfully be puniſhed, yet God afflicts him more to proue him, than to puniſh him. The Lord will rebuke him, yet not in his anger; he will chaſtiſe him, but not in his wrath. Becauſe he hath ſinned he may, I and ſhall be afflicted, and yet by that ſcourge not ſo much puniſhed as proued. Thus all things proue to the good of the elect. If they ſinne, they ſhall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; yet their puniſhment ſhall be the witneſſe of their triall, and that he path-way to their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. God will not cocker his children, but correct them; and ſtrike hardeſt where he loues moſt. The man after his owne heart ſhall roare for paine: and iuſt <hi>Iob</hi> complaines, <hi>The hand of God hath touched Mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vox clamantis in deſerto;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mee.</note> The voyce of one cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Wilderneſſe: That was S. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt:</hi> Here is another <hi>vox clamantis,</hi> the voyce of a crier;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18922:16"/>'tis in the wilderneſſe too. His ſoule was deſolate, and affected vncouth places as much as <hi>Dauid, who was like a Pellican of the wilderneſſe, and like an Owle of the Deſerts.</hi> He was the Baptiſt too,<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.6.</note> but meerely paſſiue, <hi>Baptiſmoſanguinis;</hi> he was bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with the baptiſme of affliction: and that he is a Crier as well as S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> is intimated by his name; <hi>Iob,</hi> which ſignifies a fearefull howling. We know the ſtorie of him, and the ſcope of it. <hi>ſ.</hi> the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of Gods triall of mans patience in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Each one knowes the afflictions of the man of the Eaſt, <hi>Iob:</hi> but who takes notice of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the North, our Metropolis? Here is a third <hi>vox clamantis,</hi> the voyce of one crying, I and in the Deſert. For loe Satan the Dragon hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted her as the woman in the wildernes. Nay her whole ſelfe not long agone was but a wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if you will take a Deſert for a place deſolate.<note place="margin">Rev. 12.14.</note> S. <hi>Gregories</hi> complaint was renewed, and the ruines by him deplored truly patterned in that example. <hi>Habitatores non exparte ſubtrahuntur, ſed pariter corruunt. Domus vacuae relinquuntur. Filiorum fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes aſpiciunt, et ſui eos adinteritum haeredes praecedunt.</hi> The ſtately towers of Sion were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the habitation of Satyres, her people not by degrees plucked vp, but mowed downe together in full ſwathes. Lo, a lamentable ſpectacle! The Grand-ſire, by a prepoſterous priuiledge of ſurui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, heire to his inteſtate Nephew. You might haue beheld youth the firſt borne of death, and the gray haires deſcending lateſt to the graue.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18922:17"/>The great Temple of Ieruſalem, that liuing houſe of God, the company of Chriſtians was ſo vnioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that there was ſcarce a ſtone left vpon a ſtone; a man to conuerſe in ſafetie with his neighbour. A peſtilent diſeaſe diſordered nature. The graue ſnatched what nature denied, the ſtrongeſt. <hi>Net hoc parentes heu ſibi ſuperſtites effugerit ſpectaculum.</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents were mourners for their children, and cloſed thoſe eyes which ſhould haue wept at their fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals. The graues were as full of carkaſſes as the houſes of inhabitants; and the poore remnant that were left and reſerued from this fatall captiuitie, were not ſo much the parts as the ruines of a City. <hi>Troynouant</hi> was indeed new Troy, the wretched daughter of an vnhappie mother. <hi>Beth-rapha</hi> was turned into <hi>Bochim;</hi> The houſe of health, not to an edifice but a bare place of weeping. You ſhould not haue miſ-called a matron <hi>Naomie,</hi> but called her <hi>Mara;</hi> not a beautifull ſpouſe but a diſtreſſed widow. Lo, gaſping <hi>Rachel</hi> would haue the name; for in thoſe fearefull plagues the fathers ſon of his right hand, his darling babe was but <hi>Ben-oni,</hi> the ſon of ſorrow. God Almightie had withdrawne the light of his countenance from vs; The Arke of our ſaluation was wel-neare taken, and the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting mothers, bowing themſelues for trauell, haue brought forth their firſt-borne abortiues; an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely fruit of a name, diſtractedly inquiſitiue, <hi>Ichabod;</hi> where is the glorie? <hi>Quam penè furnaeregna Proſerpinae, &amp; indicantem vidimus Aeacum!</hi> one foote was in the graue, and (O Lord) how almoſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18922:17"/>did our ſoules goe downe into the pit? There was no <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to ſaue the liuing from death; no <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> to raiſe the dead to life. The wiſe periſhed as the fooliſh, the Prieſts as the peaſants, both promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly interred together; ſo that each ſepulchre was a charnel-houſe, each graue a Golgotha. <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzar</hi> trembled for a light threat: The hand of God appeared to vs, not writing on a wall, but a whole Kingdome, grauing the name of deſolation in the black characters of the peſtilence, and each doors fatall &amp; common motto, <hi>Lord haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vpon vs.</hi> Graues were ſcarcer than houſes, and the earth more ſtreightned to receiue the dead, than the habitations the liuing. So that neceſſitie made one pit a common ſepulchre, and the whole Citie <hi>Ezekiels</hi> field. Yet loe,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</note> thoſe afflictions which ſhould haue corrected, haue hardned vs. Will a man ſpoyle his gods? ſaith the Lord: yet yee haue ſpoyled me: but yee ſay, Wherein haue we ſpoyled thee? In tythes and offerings. The Prieſt-hood is become a deriſion, the Miniſterie a contempt, and the Church robbed by contentious flocks and ſacrilegious Patrons. Wherefore ye are curſed with a curſe; for yee haue ſpoiled me (ſaith the Lord) euen this whole nation. But bring yee all the tythes into the ſtore-houſe, that there may be meate in mine houſe, and proue me now here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with (ſaith the Lord) If I will not open the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of heauen vnto you, and powre you out a bleſſing without meaſure. And I will rebuke the deuourer for your ſakes—. And all nations ſhall
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18922:18"/>call you bleſſed; for yee ſhall be a pleaſant land, ſaith the Lord of hoſts. Pride, fulneſſe of bread and deceit in the citie; Oppreſſion and barbarous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice in the countrie: theſe are the weapons which we haue whetted againſt our owne ſoules, and the broken reedes that pierced the hands of thoſe that leaned on them. How many townes may we ſee turned into open fields, religion decayed with na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the Church with the pariſhioners; land-lords metamorphoſed to wolues, ſeruants into doggs. villages into ſheep-coates, and families into ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards Curres! Becauſe the bleſſing of God was troubleſome, and the multitude of men ſeemed a burthen vnto vs, loe, the iuſt Lord hath eaſed vs in his indignation, and in a moment ſweptaway (by warre and peſtilence) aboue an hundred thouſand. He hath recompenced our ingratitude with ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and which of vs all haue not loſt a kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? O then, <hi>Haue pitie vpon vs, haue pitie vpon vs, (O yee our friends) for the hand of God hath touched vs.</hi> Yet the Lord is mercifull and gracious, and in the middeſt of iudgement hath remembred mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Our great Citie Nineueh, and her King hath repented in ſackcloth and aſhes, ſorrow and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie: and behold the Lord hath beene more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull than man. Though <hi>Ionah</hi> hath propheſied iudgements, he hath turned them into conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Behold, Syon is againe inhabited, and who can number her towers? The voice of gladneſſe is heard in her Palaces, and ſongs of thankſ-giuing in ſtead of the mourning of <hi>Hadad-rimmon: Moſes</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:18922:18"/>is heard, and the requeſt of pious gouernours now fully granted. The Lord is returned vnto the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands of Iſrael. <hi>Reioyce therfore O my ſoule, againe I ſay reioyce.</hi> O let vs remooue the Leproſie of ſinne from our ſoules, as God hath remooued the black ſpots of the Peſtilence from our bodies. <hi>O be ioyfull in the Lord all ye lands, all ſorts, all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, young men and maidens, olde men and children, praiſe yee the Lord.</hi> So ſhall God render vnto <hi>Iob</hi> ſeuen fold; the wombes of our young women ſhall be fruitfull, and your children ſhall play by thouſands in the ſtreets; the ſtrength of our young men ſhall breake a bowe of ſteele, and the gray hayres of our auncients ſhall deſcend with ioy &amp; reuerence into the graue. O then beloued quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to day if you will heare, caſt off the menſtruous cloathes of Hypocriſie and wickedneſſe, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent your ſoules, your naked ſoules as a ſacrifice without blemiſh vnto the God of your ſaluation. <hi>Come taſte and ſee how good and gracious the Lord is. Take the Cup of ſaluation, and ſing with Angels and Arch-angels, Glorie to God on high, in earth peace, and good will towards men. Wee praiſe thee, wee bleſſe thee, we glorifie thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
